<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: katas | Joseph Wilk]]></title>
  <link href="http://josephwilk.github.io//katas/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://josephwilk.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-08T15:21:29+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://josephwilk.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joseph Wilk]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[joe@josephwilk.net]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Awari Kata]]></title>
    <link href="http://josephwilk.github.io/katas/awari-kata.html"/>
    <updated>2011-03-01T14:00:32+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://josephwilk.github.io/katas/awari-kata</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>The Game</h2>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oware">Awari</a> is an ancient game originating from Africa which consists of 12 holes in the ground (called houses) split up into 2 rows of 6. Designed for two players, each player selects a row as their territory. Each house starts with 4 seeds in it.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/2009/09/image002.jpg" alt="Awari" /></p>

<h3>A round in the game goes as follows:</h3>

<p>The player picks a number of seeds from one of their houses. They sow the seeds one by one in an anti-clockwise direction around the board.</p>

<p>The number of seeds in the last sown house dictates what happens next:</p>

<ul>
<li>If there are not 2 or 3 seeds then the go finishes and its the opponents turn.</li>
<li>If the last hole is one of your opponents and the number of beads is 2 or 3 you win those beads

<ul>
<li>If you collect, then you may look at the next-to-last, and if that satisfies the same criteria, you collect those also</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>If you play so many beads that they wrap around the board (more than 11) you do not &lsquo;sow&rsquo; a bead in the house from which you picked up</li>
</ul>


<p>If an opponent&rsquo;s houses are all empty, the current player must make a move that gives the opponent seeds. If no such move is possible, the current player captures all seeds in his/her own territory, ending the game.</p>

<h3>Winning</h3>

<p>The game is over when:</p>

<ul>
<li>one player has captured 25 or more seeds</li>
<li>each player has taken 24 seeds (draw).</li>
<li>If both players agree that the game has been reduced to an endless cycle, each player captures the seeds on their side of the board.</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Challenge</h2>

<p>Attempt to write an AI to play Awari against.</p>

<p>Good luck.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
