<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: personal | Joseph Wilk]]></title>
  <link href="http://josephwilk.github.io//personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://josephwilk.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-08T19:16:10+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://josephwilk.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joseph Wilk]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[joe@josephwilk.net]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conferences and Accessibility: Please Try Harder]]></title>
    <link href="http://josephwilk.github.io/personal/conferences-and-accessibility-please-try-harder.html"/>
    <updated>2011-06-27T13:25:23+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://josephwilk.github.io/personal/conferences-and-accessibility-please-try-harder</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I speak at a lot of conferences around the world and I&rsquo;ve been happy to hear a lot of healthy debate around the diversity of the programming community. I really enjoyed and felt inspired by the talk from <a href="http://blogs.thewehners.net/josh">Joshua Wehner</a> on &ldquo;Must It Always Be About Sex&rdquo; at <a href="http://nordicruby.org/">Nordic Ruby</a> and <a href="http://rulu.eu/">Ruby Lugdunum.</a></p>

<p>It got me thinking about the issue of accessibility at conferences. I use a wheelchair and happily throw myself at any conference irrelevant of the obstacles. But not everyone is as crazy or as flexible as I am. Once at the conference the organisers are always willing to help but I wonder if we are not excluding disabled people who may dimiss the chance to talk or attend as unfeasible due to lack of information about access. Even if thats only a few people, those people are valuable members of our communities and deserve the chance to participate if they want to.</p>

<p>How would we ever know if we were discriminating, if no-one turns up in a wheelchair we are none the wiser.</p>

<p>I understand conferences are expensive and complicated events to organise. I would ask two small things of every conference organiser:</p>

<p><strong>1. Try and select an accessible venue if possible. For both speakers and attendees.</strong></p>

<p><strong>2. Make it clear on the conference website if the venue, party, hack sessions are accessible or not.</strong></p>

<p>My life was profoundly changed through speaking and attending conferences, in many ways beyond programming. I hope we can make sure anyone who wants that opportunity won&rsquo;t be put off.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
